in this video we're going to dive deeper
into how neural networks and machine
learning actually works behind the
scenes and if you're learning machine
learning you've probably come across a
diagram that looks like this which often
times if not most of the time confuses
people because it's a bunch of circles
and arrows and the explanation is
usually just as confusing well it's
simple you take your input circles and
move them through your circles and you
end up with your voila neural networks
um and so that's not really a very good
explanation at least it wasn't very good
for me when i was learning so hopefully
we're gonna break this down make it
really simple because it's not really
rocket science going into this it's not
uh simple like abc's but it's not super
complex either
so if you guaranteed if you watch this
video a few times it'll give you a big
head start on what neural networks are
and maybe even you'll be able to go and
code some yourself if you have coding
experience so here's the picture of the
neural network we're actually going to
use this diagram later but you're going
to understand it so a good way to start
is to block off this center layer we're
going to call that the black box and
this is what we've been doing if you've
been watching my last two videos on
machine learning let's just stick to the
input and output data the training data
right given this information here's the
outcome these are our input dimensions
and the output the outcome dimensions
and then somewhere that black box in
between runs over that information over
and over and over again and each time it
has a thousand knobs on that black box
and it twists a little knob just a
little bit at a time until while the
black box is tuned and we can give it
new input information and get the
correct predicted outcome
and so this video is going to dive into
the hidden layers area that black box
and how we configure it and what it does
so there's some common configuration
options no matter what machine learning
or neural network library you're using
there's some common configuration
options that you're going to come across
for configuring that neural network one
how many hidden layers do we put in that
black box we know we have an input layer
and an output layer how many layers go
in the middle and usually one is where
you need to start off with that's pretty
simple and straightforward and then how
many nodes how many neurons go in that
hidden layer
and there's a few different ways you can
kind of give yourself an answer to that
there's not an exact science to it
a good path is if your input and output
dimensions are drastically different go
somewhere in between if you have seven
input values and two output values then
yeah maybe three or four
also you definitely want to be less than
two times the input nodes if you get
bigger than two times the input nodes
you can get a situation called
overfitting where you're just not gonna
get accurate outcome
also two-thirds the input nodes plus the
output nodes that's a good kind of way
to go and so if you kind of run the math
on these three situations you'll kind of
get some ideas on what how many nodes
that hidden layer should have
an activation function this is very
important but i'm not going to go into
it right now also learning rate and
momentum are important but i'm not going
to go into those right now
lastly the iterations and the desired
error level so iterations is how many
times it goes over all the data in your
data set um the desired error level is
how accurate do you want this thing to
be
and depending on what you're going for
basically training stops until you get
to one or the other till you've gone
through say 20 000 iterations or until
your error level is 0.0001 and it's
pretty accurate whatever you set the
training is going to go till you get to
one or the other of those so that's the
configuration options that's actually
not too bad that's how you tune your
black box
so if you have a little bit of knowledge
as to what the black box is doing you
can usually tune a neural network and
move on from there and get good results
so let's go to a real example using
these circles and arrows that we have
from before we have a data set this data
set gives us fur color and weight of
animals and also tells us if those
animals were who's its or what's-its so
we want to go through all of that data
train our neural network to predict
whose it's and what's it's based on fur
color and weight um and so we've chosen
three hidden layers based on the options
that we showed you on the last slide
so let's go ahead and then get our
neural network initialize so to start
off we basically want to create a stupid
brain a brain that knows nothing so
we're gonna just randomly create a bunch
of weights you can see i'm going to get
my mouse out here you can see we've got
we've assigned a point one way to 0.38
just completely random numbers and these
neurons these hidden layer neurons and
nodes are going to also get a bias
consider them coming in with an opinion
already even though we don't know
anything
about how fur color and weight
apply to who's it's and what's it's
we're just going to start making guesses
based on our bias consider them the
liberals conservatives and libertarians
and we're going to get them all in a
room show them a bunch of real-life data
and hopefully at the end of the thing
they'll all agree
on what is truth i'm you know i'm not
going to say anything i no okay nope go
not going there moving on so that's our
hidden layers we initialize the network
with just a bunch of completely random
weights
and biases
and then moving on from there we're
going to start with the first entry in
our data set so entry number one we have
an animal for color 25 and weight of 15
and it's a who's it it's a who's it one
it's a what's it zero so now we start
moving these input dimensions through
the neural network it's called a
feed-forward neural network for that
reason so basically what we're going to
do is we're going to take both of the
input dimensions we're going to multiply
them times the weight and then add the
bias so here we go node 1 gets fur times
0.1 plus weight times 0.8 so we have our
0.1 weight and our 0.8 weight and then
we're going to add the 0.71 bias so
that's node number one so we're
basically saying let's randomly
guess
how these two nodes uh affect our
outcome let's just start with a guess
and we're going to do that for each node
a completely different set of weights
and biases here a completely different
set of weights and biases here you can
see when we get down here we're taking
fur times 0.57
plus weight times 1 and we're adding a
0.09 bias so we're basically making a
random set of guesses
and then we do the magic and then we run
all those through an activation function
and here's where the activation function
is important here's where the magic of
neural networks comes in is because
we're trying to figure out answers to
non-linear data
and so
i'm going to do a little bit of a
tangent over here and kind of show you
the difference between linear and
non-linear data linear data is a
straight line we can say that hey
um as the weight and the fur collar goes
up we know it's a greater chance of
being a who's it as it goes down it's a
greater chance of being a who's it or
what's it or hey if the fur color's high
or if the weight is high it's always
going to be a who's it right so you
could use this with some species if it's
big it's a dog if it's small it's a
mouse if it's small
smaller than a certain size there's no
way it's going to be a dog that's linear
information you don't really need a
neural network to solve answers on these
you just need a little bit of math and
the data should be pretty clear as to
how the input correlates with the output
non-linear is like this it just turns
out differently um it may be high here
and high here
or it may kind of follow some unusual
curves that are really difficult to
figure out um on your own and so that's
basically where your activation
functions come in we're going to use a
sigmoid or a tan or tan h or a tinch
depending on who you are and where you
come from uh and so we're going to
basically apply that that sum value
we're going to run it through one of
these functions and introduce
non-linearity to our neural network to
help us kind of find out the answers to
those questions so we've taken the sum
right we've taken the sum times the
weights and we've added in our bias and
we're going to run that through our
activation function now we're going to
get a non-linear guess here
and then we're going to continue running
through until we get to our outcome and
let's just throw out a number here let's
say we ran it through ran it through
activation function came through again
here and we end up with just a random
drawn out of the hat guess
that uh it's point three five one two
that it's a who's it and point seven
eight one that it's a what's it
completely wrong right our neural
network is stupid it came in with just
biases and random numbers and made a
guess that was way off so then it's back
propagation time we're going to
calculate the error in the delta which
is the difference and we're going to
adjust all the weights and the biases
we're going to go backwards through each
step and we're going to adjust these
biases and these weights
some we're not going to necessarily
adjust them all the way but we're going
to adjust them some how do we know how
much we're going to adjust them well we
do that through our configurations the
first one is learning rate learning rate
says how much should this step outcome
affect our weights and our biases and
learning rate is you almost want to
think of it as
personality types there's the slow
calculating type of person where if you
were to show them here's a cat here's a
dog they're going to say hmm
i i have some ideas show me some more
and then after you show them a whole
bunch they'll slowly
lean into the answer and then come up
with a very calculated answer that's a
low learning rate a high learning rate a
ridiculously high learning rate would be
oh you showed me a cat and a dog i
calculated the differences between the
two i know the difference
and then you show them
a really fluffy cat and they think it's
a dog because they had way too high of a
learning rate so that's what learning
rate is
and the momentum also says how should
our past outcomes affect our weights and
biases so past outcomes could say hey
that that initial weight there keeps
giving us way too high of an answer so
we're going to keep that weight kind of
going downward no matter what at least
we're going to give it a little bit of
momentum into this next step so each
step kind of takes learning rate and
momentum into account and we don't just
want to make snap judgments and we also
don't want to learn too slowly because
we learn too slowly it takes forever to
train our neural network so right it's
kind of that balance between how fast do
we want to train our data versus how
accurate do we want that data to be
that's kind of where your learning rate
and momentum come from so here's kind of
an example formula we're going to take
our learning rates we're going to
multiply the multiply it by the
difference and then multiply it by what
the actual value is now and we're going
to add that to our momentum
times our past change amount and that is
our current change amount so that's kind
of an example formula for how we use
learning rate and momentum to determine
how much to change a given weight and a
bias
so now we go through the next piece of
data yay we did it we did one iteration
through the first piece of our data set
we're not through our third iteration
yet we're gonna go to the next piece of
our data set where fur color is 15 and
weight is 35 and that's a what's it and
so we do that through each piece of data
in our data set and boom that is
considered one iteration so we have an
iteration and we have an average error
rate there and then we can determine do
we go through and do more iterations
have you requested more than that um or
have you requested that to be
an acceptable error rate and if not then
we just keep going so that's how you
train a neural network you give it
inputs
through the random weights which get
more accurate over time
biases activation function which is huge
and then you're going to calculate your
error and you're going to back propagate
some adjustments here to the weights and
biases and when you're done you get a
set of weights that are accurate a set
of biases that are accurate and you can
then run any input into it it goes
through the weights and biases and you
get a pretty good guesstimation of what
that output's going to be and that's
neural networks and machine learning in
a nutshell i hope this video helped in
the next video we're gonna actually go
back to brain.js and watch all these
configurations and all these options in
action